today we are going to talk about these
eggs
how people use them in ice cream what
they do and whether you need them or not
so let's find out about French vanilla
custard ice cream
now I can't keep track of all the
bloggers Bakers vloggers and human
beings that think they can make good ice
cream out there but when you try their
recipes online for the majority they're
awful
and also 90 of them use eggs and a lot
of them and I don't think any of them
really understand why they use the eggs
in their recipes so we're going to look
at a little bit of the history of
custard ice cream and describe what eggs
do for you in the ice cream itself
so a large egg is made up of about 70 to
78 calories seven grams of protein five
grams of fat 1.6 grams of saturated fat
it also has iron vitamins minerals and
of the two parts of an egg the yolk is
made up of vitamins a d e k B1 B2 B5 B6
B9 and b12 and the white contains
vitamins B2 B3 and B5 but does also have
B1 B6 B8 B9 and B12
French custard ice cream so the history
of ice cream goes back a long long way
generally originating in Asia but
that was a long long time ago and French
custard is really quite modern in
comparison
the US seems to believe that in 1919
French vanilla custard was invented it
surely wasn't because back in the 1700s
in Paris there were people playing with
something called fromage now that's not
cheese
but back then it was a type of frozen
dessert and in that frozen dessert they
were playing with the use of egg yolks
to better their consistency
but in reality no one truly knows where
French custard came from It is believed
that somewhere in the 1800s in paris's
very first Cafe it was served and from
that point English Monarch's French
royalty and U.S presidents have been
enjoying with the wonders of Frozen
Custard for years until the 1900s when
the Frozen Custard movement branched its
way across the world to what we know now
the egg yolks lesser thin is what
creates the custard by bonding those fat
molecules and water molecules together
creating that stable Emulsion in your
ice cream base and by gently cooking the
egg yolks themselves you create a
thicker more viscous base for your ice
cream
but French vanilla custard specifically
being one of the very first ones to come
to the rest of the world has got a quite
a unique taste
it's actually the eggy taste that you're
looking for with custard ice cream
you're looking for the imparted flavor
from the egg yolks themselves to give
you the taste of the custard truly is so
when people advertise that they're
making a custard base ice cream that's
what they're doing they're creating a
thicker more viscous Base by using the
egg yolks to bond those water and fat
molecules together then by adding other
flavors such as cocoa mint extracts even
just vanilla extract itself you start to
remove the egg taste from your ice cream
to become something more modern in
comparison to American style ice cream
or gelato which gelato does or doesn't
use eggs depending on a where you're
from and B how old the recipe is but
gelata has much less fat so you don't
get quite as much of an eggy taste when
you do use egg yolks they use it in the
right amount because they're looking for
that less than specifically to suit
their recipe size American ice cream
traditionally doesn't use any egg yolks
at all and they rely on other methods to
thicken their base so without further
Ado we're going to make some french
vanilla custard ice
okay we've weighed out everything apart
from the egg yolks so
let's get most of the components in the
pan warming up we've got our milk and
cream here we've got 300 grams of two
percent milk and
270 grams of
33 whipping cream
we've got the pan on a gentle heat and
to that we're going to not use any
stabilizer for this okay we're just
going to use the egg yolks to stabilize
this recipe don't eat any additional
So to that we're going to put in our
sugar
which is 120 grams and 32 grams of our
skim milk powder
and now our eggs
I'm going to separate four
egg yolks
noise however you want to do that is
fine with me lots of people have
different methods just going to give
this a quick stir it's not a gentle heat
so it shouldn't go too matte
[Music]
oh
foreign
[Music]
okay
so four egg yolks here I know this
container weighs 16 grams so these four
egg yolks are 92 grams so you know 78
grams 76 grams worth of egg yolks now
before your mixture gets too hot
um yeah basically cold
tempering eggs
it's a method for tempering egg yolks
has been done the same way for donkey's
years
and there really is no need to do it
that way
tempering eggs is really just a method
of cooking the egg yolks or getting the
egg yolks up to a safe temperature so
the Lesser thin actually starts acting
as it should and it bonds those water
and fat molecules together suitably
without creating
scrambled egg
take your egg yolks pour them into your
cold mixture like that
break them
and stuff
that is it
okay now put them back on your hob
nice and gently warm it up while
stirring and there is no need to do
tempering in the old-fashioned method
I'm positive that that method that
people use to temper egg yolks it has
been around since you know the French
1700s
we don't need to do that anymore
you can get the same result much safer
without any risk of scrambling your egg
yolks just by doing it like this so
we're going to bring this up to
temperature nice and slowly get it up to
that steaming point but not boiling do
not boil your custard bases
and then when we get to that stage
we'll talk about the vanilla
okay we're just getting our mix up now
to temperature the steam's coming off
I'm going to turn that down to a low
medium heat and we're just going to stir
it now for you know three four five
minutes however long that takes just to
thicken that up slightly and people
often ask what's the best way to
determine when you're ice cream base or
your custard base is ready to take off
the heat and what you're really looking
for is that back of the spoon thing okay
so when we get there and we're not that
far from it now I don't think we're
going to get our spoon and show you
exactly what that means
okay
there we are
didn't take long just two three minutes
just to get it up to that texture we're
going to take that off the heat
okay you don't like I said you do not
want to boil your custard ice cream
bases it will split the egg yolks and
you'll end up with overcooked eggs which
scrambled so
what we're looking for here is take a
metal spoon and then take it off the
back and then drag your finger down
and you can see there that line
okay
okay that is
made a mess but
it's good
that is what they mean by the back of
the spoon if you want to thicken it a
little bit more you are more than
welcome to no point stressing your
little home ice cream machine by making
this too thick a lot of home ice cream
machines cannot deal with very viscous
bases okay you will struggle and you
won't get any overrun you'll be left
with something or you know two three
maybe five percent over on very dense
and you'll lose the luxurious texture
that eggs can create in your ice cream
so
keep it around that stage and you'll be
good
vanilla pods
and one of these ones are expensive
they're in a glass jar
um
you don't want to overheat your vanilla
because you will
decimate
the vanillin inside
Okay so
these are by the looks of it Grade B
the grade of vanilla beans is determined
by the size the water content that kind
of thing these are quite skinny they're
starting to dry out so these are
definitely a Grade B Bean what you can
do you've got two options to do this you
can put this in your base while you're
warming it on the hob but you can lose
some of that flavor what I like to do
itself is
cut the bean
down the middle
just like everyone else we're going to
take out the seeds
put those in there
and we're going to put the actual pod
itself in there with it okay we're going
to put this one back in here and use
this one for something else
okay now we're gonna get our spoon
and just knock these seeds in there
stir around the residual Heat
from this custard just coming after the
hob
is plenty of heat to activate that
vanilla in your base okay you're going
to leave this in here you're going to
leave all of this sitting in here I want
all of that off there
leave it sitting in your ice cream base
ideally overnight in the fridge
okay
so we're gonna put the lid on there pop
it in the fridge 24 hours
and once that's ready we'll come back
and
talk some more about it okay take it out
of the fridge
it's been on pre-chill give it a quick
stir take out your vanilla bean and
let's get churning okay
there we go
um stop that about 10 minutes so it took
with a 10 minute pre-chill it took less
than 20 minutes somewhere around 17 to
18 very difficult seed to be exact
smells good let's get this in a tub in
the freezer
next day
let's get some of the French vanilla
custard out into the only small bowl I
have currently
so let's get some dished up see what it
tastes like
[Music]
okay nice new scoop it is the zero
number 12 the zero on so this is the
coated one
um blue cap tells you to size nice big
scoop
they've got another scoop to test that
was sent to me by someone at Sports
channel so we'll test out another video
but French vanilla ice cream
smell the vanilla
even if you do use Grade B vanilla beans
you've still got the same taste you just
don't get quite as many
seeds in there
but it's scoop nice
nicely
see what it tastes like
[Music]
nice it's
that eggy flavor comes through just just
enough
um
don't get drawn into all these silly
recipes online for ice cream I remember
one
I don't know probably two
two years ago maybe
um
a friend Joe and I were both online
looking at this guy that posted a recipe
he had 18 egg yolks
and we laughed and laughed and laughed
18 egg yolks and it was labeled as
Michelin star Vanilla
just a joke why use 18 egg yes you have
no idea what you're doing
but
the egg yolk is for the Lesser thin
and the taste so if you don't want to
use stabilizers you can use egg yolks
but you don't need to use lots of them
to produce the same result
eggs are expensive stabilizer is
expensive they're doing the same job are
they was one more natural than the other
if you know splitting hairs yes
eggs are obviously a natural thing but
if you're making vegan ice cream you
can't do that anyway so
stabilizers to me are much more cost
effective method
and actually efficient method of
stabilizing ice cream
but they will not give you the eggy
taste they will not give you that taste
of custard base ice cream because you
need that eggy flavor that egg tinge
flavor coming through that is part of
what the whole custard movement on ice
cream was it creates something different
to what the Italians were doing with
gelato when they didn't use eggs
I don't like wasting eggs in ice cream
when a stabilizer will do the same job
I'd rather not have loads of egg whites
sat in the fridge with no real
function I don't want to make
souffle or all that other kind of stuff
and let's just finally look at the cost
of using egg yolks versus stabilizer if
you bought something like xandom gum
which I'm a big fan of you know in ice
cream it's a very strong
single mix stabilizer it's you know it's
easy to buy It's relatively cheap you
can buy half a kilo of xanthan gum for
you know 15 12 to 15 Canadian
and that will go a long way so half kilo
500 grams worth of xanthan gum that
would enable you to make you know
500 kilos of ice cream
and that's probably
if you used a lot
you know you could probably drop it down
again so you probably get 550 maybe 600
kilos of ice cream out of that 500 grams
of xanthan gum so
do the math
goes a long long way if you wanted to
use the same equivalent of eggs
you know you let's say you wanted to
make two egg yolks in a recipe
um yeah it's a ton of money
but
it's a different thing
if you want to make custard ice cream
you're doing it for the flavor don't do
it for the stabilization effect of the
eggs it's just a waste of time it's very
expensive it's not as good as all the
other stabilizers that I'm currently
talking you through if you want to watch
the stabilizer video part one I'll put a
link in the description that I'll
probably put
a link at the end of the video as well
just so you can click on that and watch
that a lot of good informational
stabilizers there but
French vanilla custard ice cream
it's one of those flavors that
if you're on the edge of ice cream and
you don't know whether you like it or
not this will likely win that person
over
it's a really nice taste it's a classic
ice cream and
I hope you enjoyed learning a little bit
more about where it may or may not have
come from
and thanks very much for watching I'm
going to put a list of supporters here
on the side
um just to thank you for supporting the
channel and helping me grow any support
you can offer is amazing so thank you
very much
and I will see you next week
[Music]
thank you